[Music]
and we are live
good evening and good day everybody
welcome to episode
21 of the ask a budget show
so as you know today we are doing the
science and astrophysics uh
episode and this is where you get to ask
me any question you have
and no question is too silly or too
stupid all questions are good
i am not your school teacher or
professor i will take your questions and
i will answer them all
so keep your questions coming and as
always you have asked me a
bunch of very interesting questions and
i have picked a few of those
today for today so let's get into it
shall we
let's do it let's begin with
question number one
and this question is by priyansh bansal
we know that the andromeda galaxy is 2.5
million light years away from us
so how can we know its current position
if the light from it is 2.5 million
years old
how can we know when the collision will
occur
okay so it's a it's an interesting
question how do we know
the distance between galaxies how do we
know how far a certain galaxy
is away from us so there is something in
astronomy called a standard
candle and there are a couple of types
of standard candles
so there is one class of stars called
the sephie
variables so these are extremely
luminous
stars between 10 000 and 100 000 times
more luminous
than the sun and these stars they
pulsate
in a predictable way so there in the
luminosity goes up and goes down
in a periodic fashion in a period in a
predictable way
and the period of oscillation or
pulsation
is related to the luminosity of the star
so if we know the period of a
pulsation of the star then we know the
luminosity
and depending on how dim or bright the
star is we can actually
calculate its distance from us so the
because the apparent luminosity
decreases with the square of the
distance and these stars are so bright
then we can actually observe them in
other galaxies
like the andromeda galaxy so that's how
we are able
by observing such stars the sphere
variable stars
to determine the distance between us and
the andromeda galaxy to a very high
degree
of accuracy so this is a standard
candle basically okay this this kind of
star is called a standard candle
and there's another standard candle
which is the type one is supernova
which also has a very specific
luminosity
so based on such uh astronomical objects
we can actually determine the distance
between us
and something like the andromeda galaxy
so we know how far away it is it's about
two and a half
million light hours light years away
from us
and we know at what distance it is
coming
towards us because there is something
called dread shift and glue shift
so when something is red shifted away
from us it means it is receding away
from us it's going
further away from us and when something
is blue shifted it means it's coming
towards us
so the andromeda galaxy we know it is
coming towards us at a certain speed
and that's the basis on which we are
able to
calculate approximately when it's going
to
collide or merge with our own galaxy
so that's how it works that's how the
astronomical
observations and calculations are done
aryan asks the silliest question but
what happens when someone goes below the
mariana trench
not humans of course because of the
pressure but some machine can we find
another life form
so for those of you who don't know the
mariana trench is the lowest
uh known place in the sea floor
on the seafloor so it's it's about 11
or so kilometers below the surface of
the
ocean it is so deep that if you placed
mount
everest in it there would still be a
couple of kilometers or so
left so the top of the mount everest
would still be two
two or two and a half kilometers below
the surface of the ocean that's how deep
the mariana trench is
and i think the the pressure the water
pressure
at the bottom of the mariana trench is
about more than a
thousand times the atmospheric pressure
that we experience over here on the
surface
of the planet so it's very deep and the
the water pressure is very very high and
yet
people have gone to the bottom of the
mariana trench in special submersibles
special submarines that are purpose
built to withstand that sort of pressure
and
we have also sent a robotic uh
submarines to this place and
surprisingly
we have observed life forms there
certain kinds of fish have been observed
certain
types of crustaceans have been observed
giant amoebas have been observed
so yes life does exist even at that
intense
depth in that incredible pressure so
that's the thing about life life
life apparently is able to survive
almost anywhere
on this planet or inside the planet i
mean recently they have found certain
very ancient rocks that are millions of
years old and it seems that there are
bacteria thriving in there i mean living
in there
they are not exactly thriving but they
are there
inside this incredibly ancient rock
and they are not dead they are dormant
but they can come back to life
so that's the strange thing about life
on earth it survives somehow
anyhow so i hope that answers this
question
okay siddhant asks the photon is a
packet
of energy so
what is that energy and what is the
thing that's stopping the energy to come
out of the packet
so it's a it's a bundle of
electromagnetic
radiation it's a it's a bundle of
electromagnetic energy
there's nothing that's actually stopping
it from coming out of the of the of the
packet
because photons do lose
energy so there's something called the
gravitational red shift
so when a photon passes near a massive
object the gravity of this
massive body actually can decrease the
energy of the photon it can redshift the
photon
which means its wavelength becomes
longer in which case it loses energy
and there is something called i mean the
photons are also red-shifted because of
the expansion of the universe
so let's say a photon is emitted from a
from a distant galaxy
it travels towards us and as we know
space-time
is expanding the universe is expanding
and
what we find is that the photon when it
reaches us is red-shifted so it has
lost energy its wavelength has become
longer so it loses energy and this
brings into question the principle of
conservation of energy because
energy is supposed to be conserved in
the universe
and yet you have these photons that are
getting redshifted and that are
these photons are losing energy so the
question arises where does this energy
go
and it's perplexing but the answer seems
to be that
the photons are footing the bill
of the expansion of the universe so the
energy is going into the creation of new
space time
in the expansion of the universe so uh
that's an interesting little tidbit
so photons do lose energy the wave
packet
the quantum mechanical wave packet does
lose energy and it does elongate in
wavelength
and a photon can even be redshifted out
of existence
by either the expansion of spacetime or
by the presence of a massive object
near if it passes near that so yes
photons do lose energy the energy does
seem to leak out of the packet
by various means isn't that interesting
okay next question
akash asks uh does absolute zero
occur naturally in the universe
somewhere and what's the average
temperature of the universe
good question so first let me answer the
question of the absolute
the average temperature the average
temperature of the universe is
about 2.73 or so kelvin
which is minus 270 approximately
degrees celsius so this is the
temperature of the cosmic microwave
background radiation which is the
earliest
light that was produced in the universe
so it's kind of the
remnant of the big bang and that was
once very high energy
light but now it's extremely extremely
cold
so it's just barely above it's two and a
half two point seven three kelvin above
absolute zero so that is the average
temperature of the universe so
does absolute zero occur naturally in
the universe somewhere
no it does not absolute zero is
impossible to reach
and the reason for this has to do with
the amount of work
that's necessary to remove heat from any
substance
so the amount of work you have to do to
remove heat from a substance
increases substantially the colder
you try to go so to reach zero kelvins
we find that you would require to
put in an infinite number of work
and therefore it's impossible to reach
zero kelvin
we are able to reach very close to zero
kelvin in the lab
by cooling by by cooling various gases
and
atoms but it's impossible to reach zero
kelvin and even if you were to reach
zero kelvin
there are content mechanical effects
that co that ensure that the temperature
is never never really zero kelvin
there is still something called zero
point energy left behind
so absolute zero does not occur
naturally in the
universe anywhere it can't even occur
artificially because you cannot
do that amount of work in order in order
to bring a substance or a body
down to absolute zero interesting
good question
okay yeah this is a related question so
just as the universe has a lower limit
of temperature which is absolute zero
does it have an upper limit of
temperature too
beyond which the temperature cannot rise
any further
that's another excellent question so the
theoretically
highest achievable temperature is the
planck temperature
which is of the order of 10 raised to 32
kelvin
so that's an incredibly insane
amount of temperature it's incredibly
high 10 raised to 32 kelvin
and it is uh according to the big bang
theory when the universe was about
10 raised to minus 43 seconds old
which is the planck time that is when
the universe had this temperature
10 raised to 32 32 kelvin
so that is the theoretical
upper limit of temperature uh we are not
able to achieve
anything close to that in the lab or
anywhere else the i think the
highest that has been achieved in a lab
or in any instrument has been
around a trillion kelvin which was
probably something
that was achieved in some kind of a
collider a linear accelerator or a
collider but the plant temperature is
way way beyond that so it's the
it's almost unimaginable but that's the
theoretical
maximum that can be that can be attained
in the universe
aruni asks are black holes
denser than a neutron star what could
possibly happen if a black hole
and a neutron star would collide black
holes are indeed
denser than neutron stars neutron stars
are the densest objects
in the universe apart from black holes
so a neutron star typically has a
has a mass of 1.4 times
the mass of our sun and
it is so dense that it is it's its
radius is typically of the order of 10
kilo kilometers or so
so imagine something more massive than
the sun 1.4 times the solar mass
and it has a radius of about 10
kilometers
so that's how dense that's how compact a
neutron star is
and black holes are denser than neutron
stars they are basically uh
they are so dense that even light cannot
escape from them
so that's what a black hole is it's
denser than a neutron star what would
happen if a black hole and a neutron
star would collide they would give off a
big burst of gravitational waves a
tsunami of gravitational waves and then
the black hole
would absorb the neutron star and the
and the result would be a larger black
hole whose mass is
the mass of the black hole plus the mass
of the neutron star
minus the energy that was radiated out
in the form of gravitational waves
so that is the result of such a
collision
good good question
and again this is the say the same uh
questioner
aruni are black holes eternal
and will they keep getting bigger and
bigger and never die
if a black hole can die how would they
possibly die silently or with a big
explosion
if they can explode what would come out
of a black hole explosion very good
questions
so first of all the space space is
silent there is no gas and therefore
there is no sound
so even if you have an explosion in
space you can't hear it
it's it's not audible you can simply see
it
you can see the uh the light that's uh
that's
output from the explosion in the form of
various frequencies of radiation
ultraviolet infrared gamma rays x-rays
etc and visible light
and if something is ejected out of it it
may hit you if you are close enough
so that's the kind of explosion you
would see now
are black holes eternal well some black
holes seem to be
eternal some are not so a black hole
has a temperature and the temperature of
a black hole
is inversely proportional to its mass so
the larger a black hole is the more
massive it is
the colder it is and the smaller a black
hole is
the hotter it is that's how it works
now a hot black hole evaporates
it gives off radiation and therefore it
will decrease in size
a cold black hole if it is colder than
the
average temperature of the universe
which is the cosmic microwave background
radiation temperature
then it will actually absorb the left
behind
radiation of the big bang and therefore
it will grow in size and it will last
longer than the current lifetime
of the universe a smaller black hole a
hotter one
will evaporate and therefore it will
eventually die
in a large explosion
so yes small black holes do evaporate
and they will eventually die
larger black holes depending on how
large they are
have a lifetime that can be longer than
the
current lifetime of the universe that's
the strange thing or black holes large
ones are actually very cold
now when black holes explode what comes
out of it what comes out of a black hole
is thermal radiation it's called black
body radiation
and it is basically uh it's basically
made of
made up of uh sub-atomic particles
elementary particles
so it's a random hadronization that
gives off hadrons and photons
and even anti-matter so that's what
comes out of a black hole
when it explodes that's what is hawking
radiation
so that's how a black hole ends its life
its life
in an explosion of hawking radiation
devyanch asks
can you explain what are brown dwarfs
and how they are made
we can we say that if a body has a mass
lower than a minimum mass required for
fusion it's a brown dwarf
what is this minimum mass and how do we
distinguish between a planet
and a brown dwarf there good question
so like you said a brown dwarf is a
large
enough gaseous planet that does contain
hydrogen mostly and it is not
massive enough to sustain thermonuclear
fusion
so it is not able to sustain a
thermonuclear fusion reaction which
is what powers the stars
that's what gives off the light and
therefore these stars are somewhere
between
a planet and a star so what is the
minimum mass
the minimum mass of a brown dwarf is i
think
16 times the mass of jupiter
so that is the minimum mass required for
something called the fusion of deuterium
so in a regular star you have fusion of
hydrogen into helium
now a deuterium is an isotope
of hydrogen hydrogen has a proton in the
nucleus and an electron that goes around
it
deuterium has a proton and a neutron in
the nucleus
and an electron that goes around it so
uh when the mass of a gaseous
planet goes beyond 16 jupiter masses
that's where it is possible for it to
sustain
the fusion of deuterium for some time
and that's what can give off some kind
of energy so it is like
lukewarm it is it glows it glows
faintly in the magenta-ish
color range right and it is reasonably
hot but it's not hot enough like a star
so the mass range of a brown dwarf is
between 16 jupiter masses and
approximately 18 jupiter masses
which is the minimum threshold for
a gaseous object to become a star and
for
thermonuclear fusion of hydrogen into
helium to ignite
so that is the mass range of a brown
dwarf between
16 jupiter masses and about 80 jupiter
masses
and that is what distinguishes a planet
from a brown dwarf
so below 16 jupiter masses you have a
gas
giant planet above that and below 80
it's a brown dwarf above 80 jupiter
masses you most likely have
sustained thermonuclear fusion of
hydrogen into helium
and that's the lowest mass a star can
usually have
uditanshu asks the big bang theory says
that the universe was an infinitely
dense
point called a singularity and there was
no concept of space and time
but the singularity point must exist in
a space
so is the big bang theory misleading
well here's the thing about this big
bang singularity
we don't know if it was a big bang if
there was a singularity
at the big bang or if the space and time
space time was compressed into a
into a minimum quantum of space time we
don't know what it exactly was
but assuming it was a singularity it
wasn't in any place any point in space
or time
the entirety of the universe was
compressed into the singularity
so all of space-time was within the
singularity and the singularity we don't
know
in what it was was it in some other
dimensional
space time or not we have no idea of
knowing
as far as as we know it is the only
thing that existed anywhere
and the entire universe was within it
and something
caused this singularity to expand
violently super luminally and that's
what gave rise to the universe
so it's like asking where did the big
bang happen what was the direction
there is no direction the big bang was
everywhere everything came out of the
big bang
and similarly this singularity was
everywhere everything that we know of
everything that we can observe
was within this singularity
so this is the best theory that we have
the singularity did not exist
in a space all of space and time was
within the singularity
so this is the best theory that we have
and this is the
uh it gives us it explains
to the in the best way possible what we
observe
in the universe and therefore this is uh
as far as we know today this is the
correct theory
of the uh of the evolution of the
universe
so i would not say that the big bang
theory is misleading it is our
interpretation that needs to uh
basically encompass what really happened
there was no space time outside of the
singularity
as far as we can tell everything was
within it so i hope that clears this
doubt
okay prathamesh asks uh what is the
aurora borealis what is its significance
does it only happen in the northern
region or anywhere else
right so the aurora borealis is the
northern lights there is something
called the aurora australis
which is the southern lights which
happens near the south pole
now what exactly is this so it's uh it's
what you observe in the night sky you
have these
curtains and shimmering sheets of light
usually they are greenish pale greenish
or or
or pale pink in color and these are
waving
light light sheets or or streamers of
light
and sometimes you have different colors
you have purple
you have blue as well sometimes it's
white so what exactly is this is the
question
so these auroras they begin
in the sun so the sun has something
called
and well the sun itself has an
atmosphere
and the atmosphere is in the sun is a
very powerful magnetic field
which causes these big loops that are
called
uh solar prominences so these are big
loops of gas that go
out of this sun's corona and come back
inside so these are magnetic
field lines which cause this big gas
loops and sometimes the magnetic field
lines pinch off
and this results in a big coronal mass
ejection
which is a big explosion kind of or
of solar gas highly intense highly
uh very hot gas of plasma essentially
charged particles that are ejected out
of the sun
and there is this constant solar wind
that's coming out of the sun
and when this solar wind which is
the highly energetic charged particles
plasma
when this solar wind interacts with the
magnetic field of the earth that's when
you have this
uh phenomenon which is the aurora
borealis
or the australis so the magnetic field
of the earth is kind of you could you
could consider it to be kind of weak
near the poles near the north pole in
the south pole
and that's where these charged particles
are able to
to basically enter the atmosphere and
interact with the gas of the atmosphere
so it is the interaction of these
particles with oxygen at various
temp at various altitudes and various
pressures that causes
these different colors and it's also not
just oxygen it's also
nitrogen that that reacts with these
charged particles
so it is the reaction or the interaction
of these charged particles with oxygen
and nitrogen at various altitudes and
various pressures
that causes these different colors and
these
light shows that we observe near the
poles
so that is basically what uh aurora is
and the earth is not the only planet
that has auroras
we have observed auroras on saturn as
well and i think on other planets as
well
so it's something that occurs wherever
you have gas and wherever this
gas is able to interact with the solar
wind
because of the uh because the
magnetic field of these planets planets
is the weakest
near the poles so that is what an aurora
is
that is the significance it is the
interaction of the solar wind
with the atmosphere with the gases in
the atmosphere of the earth
okay sagar asks why don't asteroids
hit the sun asteroids do hit the sun the
sun is just so massive that it doesn't
register at all the impact is it's it's
uh
not noticeable so the sun is i think
more than 98 or 99
of the mass of the entire solar system
and an asteroid
is a negligible mass compared to that so
asteroids do hit the sun from time to
time you even have
comets that are that hit the sun or get
fragmented by the sun
and it's something that you can't really
observe because if it
does hit the sun the sun is so bright so
luminous
that you will not be able to observe
something so small and something
so dim hitting the sun but there's no
reason to believe that it doesn't happen
we have seen comets going past the sun
trying to go around the sun
in a in an orbit and these comets do get
fragmented by if they come
too close to the sun and if that happens
some fragments will indeed hit the sun
depending on the trajectory and the same
would happen to asteroids as well
so yes asteroids do hit the sun comets
also do hit the sun
there is nothing in the laws of physics
that precludes such a thing
from happening
so this is by indra ud with today's
technology
are we capable enough to divert a large
incoming
asteroid in short can we survive
a dinosaur-like situation a good
question
so what happened to the dinosaurs is
that
an enormous asteroid or comet
impacted the earth it is believed to be
around
10 to 15 kilometers in diameter
an enormous space rock which hit the
earth
in mexico's yucatan peninsula we have
found the impact crater
it's called the chichalub impact crater
so this is what happened during the time
of the dinosaurs about 65 million years
ago
and it caused a disastrous
uh cataclysm on the planet
and the great number of species of
significant majority
of the species of animals and plants on
the planet were wiped out because of
this
a few survived and most of the dinosaurs
died out in this so this is the
prospect that uh looms upon humanity
because sooner or later this sort of
thing is going to happen again
so are we capable enough to divert such
a large incoming asteroid
so um how would we do that the uh
popular science fiction movie strategy
to deal with this is to
launch a nuclear missile at this
incoming asteroid
however you find that even if you were
to detonate a big very powerful nuclear
bomb maybe 50 megatons or so
aton near an asteroid it would merely
fragment the asteroid
and instead of one large asteroid
hitting the earth you would have a bunch
of fragments
hitting the earth in multiple multiple
locations so it's not the best
strategy i think the best way to
divert an asteroid is to use something
called a gravity tractor
so what you would do is you would send a
spacecraft near the asteroid
uh maybe a year or so before it's
supposed to intersect with the earth's
orbit
and you would use the gravity of this
satellite or spacecraft to slowly slowly
slowly nudge the
incoming asteroid away from earth's from
the trajectory of the earth's orbit
so this is called gravity tractor or so
that's
what what could basically deflect
it just enough so that it will miss the
earth
so this is theoretically possible uh
have we ever tried
this on an asteroid just to see if it
works we have never tried it
and recently i think there was some
analysis done whether we can we are able
to prevent something like this happening
and it
it was found that as of today we are not
able we don't have the ability
to prevent uh massive asteroid strike
so as of today with the technology that
we have we do have the technology
theoretically
to deflect an asteroid provided we
know it's coming and we are able to
predict this the thing is that there are
so many asteroids in the solar system
many of them are near earth's asteroids
some of them are of particular concern
further down the line 10 20 30 50 years
down the line
so there are these uh space watching
programs i started watching programs
that keep
track of these uh potentially dangerous
asteroids
but there are so many asteroids in the
solar system millions and millions of
them
that's it it's impossible to try to know
about every one of these
so there's always the possibility that
something will come out of somewhere and
could possibly uh pose a significant
danger to earth
so in short as of today we uh
basically don't have the capability
to to divert a large incoming
asteroid if today if astronomers were to
were to find suddenly a new asteroid
that's
going to hit the earth in six months
time we are most likely doomed
most likely it will be very difficult to
scramble a mission a space mission
in time to do something about this if
you find something that's
going to happen maybe one year down the
line it may
give us a better chance ideally we want
something
to be known at least a few years
beforehand so that we can plan
properly and in that case it should be
possible to divert
or deflect an incoming asteroid but at
short notice
it's basically impossible so one hopes
it doesn't happen anytime in the near
future
this sort of thing happens once in about
65 to 100 million years
so it's been 65 million years since the
last time it happened so
so it's best that we are prepared for
this
so that's the answer sir
okay akash asks how can we detect
exoplanets hundreds and thousands of
light years away
and know their size density mass etc yet
we can't figure out what
is the gravitational anomaly that
affects the orbit of pluto in our own
solar system
despite being so close comparatively
excellent question
so how do we detect exoplanets
hundreds of light years away so there
are a couple of
methods of doing it one of the methods
is to
observe a star and try and see if there
is any periodic
periodic dimming of the star so if a
star
is observed to dim regularly
in a periodic manner it it would
indicate that there is something
that comes between us and the star
between uh the line of sight
and that is something that indicates a
planet and deter
depending on how far the star is and how
much is the uh
dimming of the light in a periodic
manner we can actually determine the
size of the or the other size of the
planet that is
coming between us and the star the other
one is to
detect whether there are any
oscillations in the in the period
and things like that so there are
certain indirect ways of observing
uh whether there is an uh exoplanet or
not and
once you know about an exoplanet if it
transits a star you can actually try and
detect
the spectra of light that come from it
from there and then we can determine
roughly the kind of composition etc it
has
so this is a very hit and miss kind of
thing it it
basically we can do this only if
the plane of the orbit
of this exoplanet is exactly between us
and its parent star so we have detected
thousands of exoplanets but we have
missed
millions because they are not so
inclined
so the statistical likelihood is
basically one in
i don't know at least thousands or maybe
millions and yet we have found
thousands now when it comes to the
gravitational
anomaly that affects uh the orbit of
various uh
of pluto etc so we have detected that
there seems to be something massive
beyond the orbit of pluto that is
causing certain
uh kuiper belt objects to have a strange
inclinations
and it's behaving it's causing them to
behave strangely
so there is the possibility that
something is lurking out there
but we are talking about something
massive but something dark and that's so
far away
and there is nothing that that it is
transiting
so if there was something between the
earth and the sun then we could observe
it transiting the sun
and it would be illuminated by the sun's
light but if something is that far away
way beyond the orbit of pluto then the
sun's
light over there is extremely dim and if
it is a
darker body or a redder body it's almost
impossible to detect it at such an
incredible distance
and there is even the hypothesis that it
could be
a primordial black hole of some sort in
which case it's absolutely impossible to
detect it
and yet it would have the same
gravitational effect as
a planet of the same mass and these are
the reasons why it is
so hard to detect it we may never be
able to detect it even if it does exist
uh the planets that have been detected
thus far have been
gas giants and pluto itself is quite
bright because
it's its surface is quite icy and very
reflective
so the objects we have been able to
detect thus far have been very
bright either large and bright or small
and shiny
and it is known that there are certain
objects that are that are quite dark
that are full of there are coated with
hydrocarbons of some kind
some of these are full of carboniferous
material etc
and this would be quite dark so these
are some of the reasons why
it's very hard to detect an object like
that especially at such a large distance
away
way beyond the orbit of pluto so we may
be able to find it
if it does exist or we may perhaps never
if we do find it it will be through
great through a great deal of luck
more than anything else
okay this is uh from deepak singh rana
namaskar deepak uh kindly explained the
role and importance of the large
hadron collider cern in modern science
and its future of humanity what led to
the scientists to put large
lord nataraja's statue outside the
facility
as there are some ongoing conspiracies
about the link
of the statue and the activities going
on there i have been asking the square
since the last seven live sessions i am
very sorry i didn't see your question
i found it thankfully so please clear
this up
if you know anything okay deepak so what
is the large hadron collider
the large hadron collider is a powerful
particle accelerator it accelerates
protons mostly charged particles protons
to almost the speed of light so it
accelerates them to extremely high
velocities
and it imparts enormous amounts of
energy
to these particles and it
collides them head-on so proton beams
colliding head-on
and when two protons collide in this
manner
they they get smashed up and a whole
bunch of debris flies out and the debris
that flies out depends not just on the
mass of the two protons but also on the
energy that is imparted to the protons
so a lot more comes out because of the
equals mc square relationship
and it is hoped that it is by observing
these
these collisions and these high energy
wreckages of particles that we may find
some new physics or some new phenomena
or some new particles
and this uh super collider is able to i
think
create millions of collisions per second
when it is running and fully operational
so
this is what has enabled us to uh
to discover the last missing link in the
standard model of physics which was the
higgs boson
which is the gauge boson that imparts
mass
to various uh subatomic particles so
without the higgs boson there would be
no mass in the universe
and the universe would be a very
different place so this is the one major
discovery this part
this particle accelerator has done so
that's what the large hadron collider is
it is the most
expensive scientific instrument ever
ever built
it's the most powerful collider ever
built
and it has succeeded in discovering this
last
missing piece of the standard model
is there any conspiracy going on there
none that i know of
yes there is a statue of the lord shiva
lord nataraj
outside of cern
and i think it has been placed there as
tribute or homage to the god that is
believed to be the creator and eventual
destroyer of the universe
which is kind of in line with the big
bang theory i mean the creation at least
is in line we don't know how the
universe will
end eventually but if it is indeed
destroyed at some point
it is well one could say that it is the
lord shiva who does this
so that is the only reason why the god
has been put there he's the creator and
the eventual
eventual destroyer of the universe so it
is
in honor of this great god that his
statue is put there there is no link
there is no scientific reason
for putting the statue there there is no
link between the statue
and the scientific experiments that are
going on inside and as far
as i know there is no conspiracy of any
kind
in uh in cern or in the large hadron
collider so that is the best
i can answer this question uh
i know that you're looking for some some
conspiracy link i am very sorry i don't
have any answer to any conspiracy
i don't know of any conspiracy or any
scientific link between what's happening
uh scientifically and inside this
facility and the statue
so as far as i understand it's just to
honor the great god
who creates and eventually destroys the
universe
that's all i can answer okay thank you
okay so man asks
uh what are your views on the global
warming phenomenon
is it a natural process by being
accelerated by human activities or is
the situation
really very acute as portrayed
will mass electric vehicles adoption
stop global warming
so global warming is a reality
global warming does happen it's been
happening for
ever since the planet
was born global warming has been an ever
present feature of planet earth
from the very beginning and the earth's
atmosphere and climate etc has seen
massive changes over the
over the eons so it is a natural process
yes but
does do human activities accelerate or
affect
global warming definitely yes and even
if you look at the past 20 30 40 000
years of
human history there has been significant
change
in the climate so there has been a
massive ice age the last glacial
uh minimum which was around 20 to 20 000
years ago or so before today
there was the younger dryas period which
was a sudden
surge of cold weather which happened
about 13 to 12 000 years ago
and then there is the little ice age
which happened a few centuries ago and
now there is this global warming that's
happening
so this is something that keeps
happening over time but yes
the human activities are indeed
as far as we know from the data that we
have there the human activities are
indeed
causing and speeding up the rate of
global warming right now so this process
began
with the industrial revolution when the
western world started
emitting uh carbon into the atmosphere
in large quantities and today we have a
great deal of
excess of all this which has been
released into the atmosphere and this is
causing the effect of global
warming because there are greenhouse
gases etc that are part of this
so yes it is definitely something that's
happening
can we stop it i doubt it very much it's
going to happen whether we like it or
not
we can try and slow down our
contribution to global warming
which even even that is uh quite
difficult to achieve because every
country does what is best for itself and
its national interest and it's very
difficult to
achieve certain targets so
it's going to happen whether we like it
or not the situation i don't know how
acute
it is but yes we are moving towards
a time in which the temperatures will on
average be
a couple of degrees maybe two or three
degrees higher than what they used to be
in the past so that is a significant
change yes
and it's going to cause a great deal of
changes
in the climate in the sea levels etc uh
very low-lying
countries like the maldives and certain
south pacific islands may entirely
disappear
um coastal regions and coastal cities
may be greatly affected
by this rise in sea levels so yes we
will see this in the coming of
decades maybe century or so yeah it will
happen
will uh the adoption of electric
vehicles in
in massive numbers stop global warming
well it all depends on how we are
producing electricity even if we stop
using uh
these combustion engines and stop using
petroleum and gasoline diesel petrol etc
but if we are still generating
electricity using the burning of coal
or any such dirty method then even if
you adopt electric vehicles worldwide
it's going to make no difference
whatsoever because we are still
generating electricity by burning coal
or by burning some other fuel so the
best way to
slow down this process is to use
renewable energy
uh solar energy wind energy hydro
thermal energy
etc that would be the or nuclear energy
so these are the ways in which we can
possibly slow down the
global warming but just adopting
electric vehicles will really make no
difference as long as electricity is
produced the way
we currently are producing it to the
largest extent because i think most of
the universe
of the uh electricity produced worldwide
i think a
major portion of it is produced by
burning coal and that is just as bad as
using a diesel or petroleum
burning vehicle so that is the key
it's to use sustainable sources
of energy
okay this is by ridi
if there are galaxies which recede away
from each other
faster than the speed of light what will
be the time dilation
accordingly a good question
so time dilation is something that that
happens when you go
at a relative when something travels at
a relativistic velocity
which is a significant percentage of the
speed of light
so if you have two twins one who remains
on earth
and the other twin goes on a rocket
rocket which travels
let's say at a tenth of the speed of
light
and that that person who is in the
rocket may experience
let's say a journey of let's say one
year
and when this person comes back to earth
after traveling at the speed of 0.1 the
speed of light
for one year he or she may find that
their
twin has aged much more than one year
and how much this twin has aged can be
calculated
using the uh principles of special
relativity so this is called time
dilation
right so when something travels at a
significant
percentage of the speed of light you
experience time dilation
now we know that there are galaxies and
portions
of of the observable of of the universe
that are receding for us
of receding away from us at the speed
of light or faster than the speed of
light which means we can never observe
them
again now it's not happening because
these galaxies are traveling within
space time
faster than the speed of light it's
because the space time itself is
expanding
faster than the speed of light so there
is this
speed limit in the universe which is the
speed of light but
it doesn't mean that the space time
itself cannot expand faster than that
space time itself can expand faster than
the speed of light
in which case there is no time dilation
what whatsoever
the time dilation only happens when
you're traveling within space time
at a significant portion of the speed of
light
but if you are embedded inside space
time and that space time itself is
expanding that fast
then there is no time dilation
whatsoever
so it's something that's quite
complicated and and hard to wrap your
mind around
but that is one of the strange
things about the universe that's one of
the mysteries of the universe so super
luminal
expansion is indeed possible and it does
not violate the speed limit
as long as it is space time itself that
is expanding this fast and we know it is
in certain portions
of the universe so the ex so the
observable universe is about
93 billion light years in diameter
and every minute as we speak there are
stars and galaxies that are
going that are basically going outside
the observable universe because they
start to recede away from us
faster than the speed of light so that's
happening
as we speak the cosmic horizon is
shrinking
eventually the only thing that we will
be able to see
in the universe will be just the local
cluster of galaxies
and maybe eventually it will just be our
own galaxy combined with andromeda
so that's the thing that's the future
that awaits us provided we
stick around as a species for another
five billion or so years
in which case things will be very
strange and very interesting
okay dungar singh chauhan if nothing
can escape black holes
then why don't they just suck up the
entire universe
so it's like saying if there is a very
big
fish why doesn't it suck up the entire
ocean
right so even if
nothing can escape a black hole it
doesn't mean it's going to suck up the
entire universe
right a black hole is a certain size and
it has a certain
event horizon and it absorbs
permanently or more or less permanently
only something that crosses the event
horizon
if something is outside the event
horizon it doesn't suck it up the
the black hole is not like a vacuum
cleaner it goes everywhere and sucks
everything uh inside it's not like that
a black hole can sit in its corner of
space time
quietly for almost forever without ever
coming into
uh without ever interacting with
anything anything else
if it is in such a location of space
time where there is very less
where there are very less stars or
galaxies around
so um so even if you look at the
supermassive black hole at the center of
the milky way it's not really active
it's not really sucking anything in it
is an enormous
supermassive black hole its mass is of
the order of
millions of times the solar mass and yet
it's it's sitting quietly
at the center of our galaxy it's not
doing anything
it is basically holding the galaxy
together and it's not sucking in
any matter because nothing is as far as
we can see from here
crossing the event horizon there are a
bunch of stars
that are very close to it and they are
moving very rapidly
because of the uh proximity
to this massive object and yet they are
not being sucked in they are simply
orbiting
the black hole so a black hole is not
necessarily something that's going to
vacuum clean everything and suck
everything in
it can just sit there essentially
forever
and not suck anything in depending on
where it is located
so that's how it is so i hope that
answers this question
okay i think i've taken 19 or 20
questions let's take some
live questions now
and i saw a question earlier i don't
know where it is now
but somebody asked me that are the
dinosaurs all extinct
or are some dinosaur i mean did they all
die out 65 million years ago
and the answer is that there was indeed
a disastrous cataclysm 65 million years
ago
the chick-fil-a impact event in which
the majority
of dinosaurs died out but
a certain category or class of dinosaurs
survived the avian dinosaurs
and their descendants are still alive
those are
the birds so the birds are dinosaurs
the dinosaurs who lived about 65 million
years ago had feathers
most of the dinosaurs that is now found
seem to have had feathers
even the great t-rex may have had
feathers
so birds are essentially nothing but
dinosaurs these are the dinosaurs that
survived
that horrific day
and so that the closest living relative
to the t-rex
is the is the common chicken
so dinosaurs did not all die out the
non-avian dinosaurs died out they all
perished
but the avian dinosaurs survived and
they are still
around today your favorite bird is a
dinosaur
whether it's the peacock or the turkey
or the chicken or the hawk eagle
whatever it is
these are all descendants of dinosaurs
these are all dinosaurs
these are living breathing dinosaur
dinosaurs
isn't that interesting
okay let me find some interesting
questions
thank you very appreciate it thank you
very much
okay this is by jyoti what do you think
about the technology required for
interstellar travel faster than the
speed of light
what are the different ways in which we
can achieve it there are a couple of
ways
hypothetically perhaps possibly
that we could conceivably
try and tr travel
faster than the speed of light one is
the
uh favorite staple of science fiction
which is the wormhole
which is essentially uh something that
connects two far apart regions of
space-time together
it's like a tunnel through space-time
and it connects two very distant regions
of space time together
so theoretically it may be possible it
is something that
tends to pinch off and close into two
black holes
but if you have something like the
theoretical hypothetical cosmic strings
then cosmic strings could possibly keep
a wormhole
open and if it is large enough wide
enough then it may be possible for human
beings to travel
through one so that is one theoretical
hypothetical possibility of traveling
faster than the speed of light or babies
basically
basically bypassing the speed of light
the other one is the
warp drive which seems to perhaps be
possible
there are certain solutions of
einstein's equations of general
relativity which
may make it possible theoretically
to construct a warp drive engine
which would require immense amounts of
energy but it may hypothetically or
theoretically
be possible so these are two possible
ways
in which it may perhaps be
feasible to travel either faster than
the speed of light or to bypass the
speed of light light itself
but we are nowhere close to doing
anything like this
we are basically stuck at below the
speed of light and we are just trying to
construct better rocket engines or maybe
to
uh create technology such as the light
sail
which may allow us to accelerate uh to
real
relativistic speeds so that is the best
we can think of
right now this uh is all
firmly in the realm of science fiction
either wormholes or warp drives
but theoretically it may be possible
okay manima asks can life exist
without carbon and oxygen it may be
possible
uh it is not an inc unconceivable that
there may be different kinds of life
or maybe non-carbon based life maybe
silicon based life forms it is possible
so the uh search for life is primarily
something that we do
in the so-called goldilocks zone around
stars
which is the zone at which it is
possible to have liquid water or flowing
water
so we are basically trying to find
exoplanets that are in that
habitable zone around their parent stars
but it is possible uh
that there may be other forms of life as
well for example you have this uh
moon of saturn called titan which is
rich in hydrocarbons it has a very
interesting
cocktail of hydrocarbons and very
interesting chemistry out there
so it is conceivable that you may have
non-carbon-based and non-water-based
life over there and it could something
that could happen in other on other
planets as well
on exoplanets as well so it is not
necessarily that
all life it is not necessary that all
life has to be based
on carbon and oxygen only there could be
definitely there could be other forms of
life which we may we may not have
thought of
it is definitely definitely possible
okay yash asks please tell us about
tectonic weapons is it possible to
create earthquakes artificially
well i think if you detonate a powerful
uh
nuclear weapon underground it is going
to cause something like an earthquake
so that is one way of having a tectonic
kind of effect
as far as i know such weapons don't
exist as
far as i know if any such research is
being done it is being kept
under wraps and it would need immense
amounts of energy
to actually shake the earth's crust in
that manner
so as far as we know as far as the
publicly available
information is concerned such weapons
don't exist
is it possible to create such a weapon
definitely
we could use a nuclear weapon or some
other form of energy very energetic
uh weapon or process in which case you
could have something like this
so it is not science fiction it is
definitely possible if you can harness
that amount of energy and use it
to vibrate or shake or disturb the crust
of the earth
it is possible hypothetically does it
really exist as of today
i it is very doubtful
if it does exist it is highly classified
so that's with what we know about this
about this
hypothetical technology
okay do we have something else
okay dhyana asks uh can we namaskar
can we put an artificial satellite on an
asteroid
that could help scientists save fuel as
it can travel on the asteroid
forever well satellites are typically
to be placed in orbit around our planet
so that they can perform a variety of
tasks whether it is
remote sensing or telecommunications
or whether it is broadband or something
so you would typically have a satellite
in low earth orbit around 100 kilometers
above our planet
or in polar orbit or in geostationary
orbit
or something like that right so so
there's a number of there's a variety of
orbits that you could place
a satellite in and you don't want to
have a space rock
orbiting the earth at that sort of
altitude you just don't want to have
that
so it would not make a great deal of
sense to put an artificial satellite all
the way on
on an asteroid either sending in a
satellite all the way there
in which case it would not serve any
purpose for us here on earth
because the asteroids are really really
really far away from the earth
the the asteroid belt is between the
orbits of mars and jupiter
which is a very large distance away from
earth
so it would not really serve any purpose
for us or here on earth and to
bring an asteroid here near earth and
put a satellite
on it would basically be pointless as we
can just put a satellite in earth orbit
itself
so we would basically save the most
amount of fuel just
by placing a satellite in earth's orbit
instead of
trying to involve any kind of asteroid
in this matter so a satellite
can for a very long period of time
remain in earth's
orbit could happen for centuries if you
put it in a certain orbit
so i hope that answers your question
dhyana
okay do we have anything else
okay manima asks space colony on mars or
on artificial self-sustaining planet aka
mega satellite
which seems more realistic i would say a
colony on mars is more realistic because
it would take less resources
than constructing an enormous mega
satellite
so to send people on mars you would need
to have
a large rocket or a number of large
rockets which can
reasonably easily be constructed here on
earth and
once these people reach mars they could
re
they could use the resources on mars
itself to construct
a color name so you could possibly have
some
robots that do mining on mars and
extract metals etc
and construct a colony or something like
that so that is
definitely something that could happen
in the next two three decades
possibly but constructing a mega
satellite
would basically take a great deal more
resources
than just sending people to mars and
doing this there
therefore it is much more realistic to
have a space colony on mars with a few
people
than having a mega satellite anywhere
in the solar system so the mars colony
is much more feasible
than a mega satellite
okay let me take a couple of more
questions
so this is a similar question why can't
we just make an artificial earth like a
spaceship instead of terraforming a
whole planet
we could get raw materials from
different planets and convert them into
things we need
well it would it would need a great deal
of power
and engineering capability to be able to
take raw materials from various planets
and
create a and construct a whole new
planet out of that
that would that would basically need you
to be
most likely a kardashev type 2
civilization you would have to go beyond
a kardashev type one
civilization so type one civilization is
one that can harness the
entire resources of its home of its home
planet
and a type two civilization is one that
can harness the entire resources of its
home solar system so to do what you're
proposing one would need to be somewhere
between type one
and type two so it is not easy it's
extraordinarily hard
to achieve that uh level
of engineering capability so it is way
more easier just to go to another planet
and try to modify with its its
atmosphere to make it more
earth-like and more habitable for human
beings
than to construct a whole new planet out
of raw materials
so i think it's easier to try and
make a planet like mars more habitable
for human beings
okay soviet asks why can't we construct
a colony on the moon instead of mars
well you're right it's easier to
construct a colony on the moon
it's right next door we can reach the
moon
in a couple of days depending on how
powerful or how fast your rocket is
and yeah it's it's close by so and it
takes
almost a year to reach mars one way so
there is a
much greater risk in that amount of
space travel and
it's much easier to construct a colony
on the moon the problem with the moon is
that it's
its gravity is very small so if you
weigh 60 kilos on earth you will weigh
only 10 kilos
on the moon secondly there is no
atmosphere on the moon
so you would always need to be uh inside
a space suit if you ever went outside
your space colony and the low gravity
has
harmful effects on the human physiology
in the long run
which is well known the gravity of mars
is lower than that of the earth but it
is still much greater than that of the
moon
so it is a better long-term prospect for
human habitation
way better than the moon and it does
have an atmosphere
which can hopefully someday in the
future be uh augmented and made more
earth-like
if we can develop that capability
so these are the reasons why the the
moon
is not that attractive a target
for constructing a long-term space
colony than mars itself
mars would be a much better prospect for
the long-term future
of humanity as a secondary home
for our species the moon is not is not
anywhere close to the kind of
uh benefits that mars would give you
it's much larger
there are many more resources there's a
lot of water there
so mars is overall better than the moon
okay
okay let me take one more one or two
more questions
okay
is there any possibility of black rays i
have never heard of black rays i'm very
sorry i don't know what that is
uh black rays i can't imagine what that
could be
sorry i'll try and look it up and if
something like that exists
or is hypothetically possible i'll try
and answer that in the next session
i apologize i don't have an answer to
this question
do i believe in aliens i believe it is
very likely that uh that life does exist
on other planets
maybe even within our own our own solar
system it is
statistically highly likely because
statistically there are more than 10
raise to 20
at least exoplanets in the universe
10 with 20 one with 20 zero zeros behind
it
so even if life is a one in a million
occurrence
you still have more than a trillion
planets with life on them
and even if intelligent life is a
one-man
in a million thing you still have
billions of planets that would have
intelligent life
so i think it is extremely likely that
aliens do exist
intelligent life forms the only question
is why haven't we
met any or or detected any signs of them
so that is the fermi paradox there are a
number of hypothetical
uh answers to it so that's a whole
different question but
do i believe in aliens i think it is
extremely likely
that aliens do exist so
that's the answer
okay let me take one more question
okay it is by ayush ray jaiswal
can we use light source as a fuel so
that we can achieve the speed of light
well there is something called radiation
pressure
so just as you if i if i
punch my fist into my into my into my
palm it's going to impart a force on my
palm
the same way the light that is that's
hitting my pa my palm
also does exert an actual
pressure on on my palm so there is
something called a light
sail which can hypothetically be used
to accelerate objects to a significant
percentage of the speed of light a light
sail is something that uses the
pressure of light itself so you have a
very thin
and very uh very light
reflective sail kind of object which is
usually made up of some kind of metal
and if you were to focus laser beams on
it
then the pressure that this laser beam
imparts on the light sail
can very quickly accelerate that that
light sale to
maybe 10 or 20 percent of the speed of
light so that is a technology that could
be
uh achieve achievable in the next 10
or 15 years so there is a project that
is right now
ongoing that could possibly achieve this
in the next
decade or maximum two decades but
can it uh can we achieve the speed of
life light itself
no there is nothing that can achieve the
speed of light
the faster you go the more massive the
object becomes that is called
so that that is that is the thing about
relativity that the faster
a mass travels the more massive it gets
and that is why it is impossible to
achieve the speed of light because you
would
the the mass would basically become
infinite
so there is nothing that can conceivably
according to the laws of physics
accelerate
an object to the speed of light but
light sales can
theoretically achieve 20 or even 30
of the speed of light so that is the
best we can do
within the laws of physics as we
understand them as of today
shall i take one more question okay one
final question
okay um 95 of the universe is
non-physical
dark matter and dark energy both as of
now are non-physical effects
well uh unfortunately that is not the
case
95 of the universe is invisible to us
it is physical because it has a physical
effect
and that is how we know it is there dark
matter
interacts via the gravitational force by
a gravity
and we can see its physical effects it
does cause
gravitational lensing which is a
physical effect so we know it is there
it is a physical thing but we just don't
know what it is made of
so dark matter is about 20
or so percent of the uh composition of
the universe roughly dark energy also
has a physical effect it causes the
accelerating expansion of the universe
it acts like an anti-gravity kind of
force
so that also is quantifiable it is
physical and this unknown energy is
about 70 percent
of the entire mass energy composition of
the universe
so these are physical quantities these
are physical things these are not
unphysical or non-physical effects
so science and physics is concerned with
physical phenomena
observable or measurable phenomena and
dark matter and dark energy are both
quantifiable measurable and observable
in one way or the other
so these are physical effects
or materials or matters or forces
whatever they are
right so we don't know what it is but we
know it is there so it is definitely
very much
physical so i hope this clarifies
this particular matter all right my
friends
uh i'm done for the day thank you very
much for participating very interesting
questions
and we will continue doing this episode
week after week so we will have one more
episode about this particular topic
once again next week but for today thank
you very much for
your viewership thank you for
participating thank you for your
comments
thank you for your questions and i will
see you
in the next episode i wish you a good
night
good day wherever you are take care see
you
bye